<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Grant's Garden]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Work and writing in progress]]></description>
        <link>https://garden.grantcuster.com</link>
        <image>
            <url>https://grant-uploader.s3.amazonaws.com/og-images/index.png</url>
            <title>Grant&apos;s Garden</title>
            <link>https://garden.grantcuster.com</link>
        </image>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2024 00:37:55 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://garden.grantcuster.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2024 00:37:55 GMT</pubDate>
        <managingEditor><![CDATA[Grant Custer]]></managingEditor>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[2024-09-02-19-57-44-Artisty-and-AI-the-Model-Makers]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[# Artistry and AI: The model makers

Some of the most interesting responses I saw to Ted Chiang's piece:

Mat Dryhurst [tweet](https://x.com/matdryhurst/status/1830204253102538920):

> The easy unlock re the cyclical AI art culture war that will seem obvious in retrospect is that the people creating models are artists
>
> The same rules apply as in Chiang's piece. Some intervene in a deliberate manner in every stage of the process, some make rote and inelegant choices 

and this [thread](https://x.com/timhwang/status/1830630445072961903) from Tim Hwang again emphasizing model making

> for chiang, good art is about *choices*, lots of them
>
> if choice is art, pretraining a model is absolutely an art, and fine-tuning nearly always is too
> 
> model architectures, dataset selection, evaluation structures are  all deeply matters of curation, taste, and aesthetics
>
> like many people, chiang gets lost in the “push button, get art” implementations we see in the market
> 
> he blunders here 
> 
> chiang mistakes these apps as reflecting something *inherent* in language models as a technology, rather than a design choice on the part of the designer
> 
>this is why the analogy connecting LLMs as an art form to gaming as an art form is so important
>
> game design is an artistic act, but whether or not the interactivity that game allows is artistically worthwhile is separate question, defined by choice on the part of the designer

These were _fun_, I like to imagine a world of weird models put forward as art objects to explore.

Does it seem like this is where things are headed thougn?

I haven't been thinking this way. I think because I've mainly been focused on using models in a programming context, where I'm looking for capabilities to fit into apps.

And the narrative so far has just been scaling things up further and further, so that all kinds of responses are available within a model, you just need to prompt yourself into it.

I'm trying to think of things where the model's 'personality' or at least 'angle' is interesting. I've seem people speak about Claude that way, but even if there are edges where you can see the personality there, it still seems to me it's in such a capability race that I can't see real aesthetic-based curation happening. Like I can't imagine them choosing to leave out certain data because it doesn't fit the vibe if the data would contribute to performance.

Or, like, Midjourney has/had an aesthetic, but it feels like their goal is/will be 'anything you want to create, in any style' that just seems to be the way these push.

Maybe the variety shakes out more after the big capability race settles a bit, maybe synthetic data gets all capabilities to a point where more curation is possible and wanted.

And the idea of curating a dataset to define a model, does have some nice analogies - it feels like breeding grape varieties for wine or something. Where your intelligence about adding just a hint of this edgy data to balance out a mostly sophisticated set - and then a tasting with notes like 'a hint of this subreddit'.

But in that example what is it you actually do with the model? Maaaybe it's a chatbot? No I think better if it's language then it's some sort of interactive storytelling - in which case the big thing it would need to be is distilled - so that you could see it's value immediately because the potentiol for slop is so high...

So it's fun to think about but gets very fuzzy.

To pin something for another day: part of the question is how to distinguish a subtle, artist-trained model/work versus just a huge model prompted into that space. Part of it maybe that you couldn't jailbreak out of the artist model? In that way maybe it is like a game design...







]]></description>
            <link>https://garden.grantcuster.com/2024-09-02-19-57-44-Artisty-and-AI-the-Model-Makers</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://garden.grantcuster.com/2024-09-02-19-57-44-Artisty-and-AI-the-Model-Makers</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2024 19:57:44 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[2024-09-01-21-16-36-Zoom]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[# CSS Zoom

Redid CSS zoom method again. Hopefully a base to build on for future projects at https://github.com/GrantCuster/zoom

![Zooming in on the sloth](https://grant-uploader.s3.amazonaws.com/2024-09-01-21-15-17.gif)
]]></description>
            <link>https://garden.grantcuster.com/2024-09-01-21-16-36-Zoom</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://garden.grantcuster.com/2024-09-01-21-16-36-Zoom</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 21:16:36 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[2024-09-01-11-06-33-Ted-Chiang-Why-AI-isnt-going-to-make-art]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[# Ted Chiang: Why AI isn't going to make art

More response writing! Here we go. Same rules, don't summarize, pick out what's interesting to me even if it leaves a bunch of other stuff out.

First his definition:

> art is something that results from making a lot of choices.

In the case of prompting to generate text or images, he argues, you are making very few choices.

> What I'm saying is that art requires making choices at every scale; the countless small-scale choices made during implementation are just as iportant to the final product as the few large-scale choices made during the conception. [...] the interrelationship between the large scale and the small scale is where the artistry lies.

This is part of why I like making prototypes, going through the process of implementation, lots of small choices show up to be made, some of them suggest rippling, larger choices.

> I doubt you could replace every sentence in a thriller with one that is semantically equivalent and have the resulting novel be as entertaining.

This actually seems like a doable generative experiment...

Another big distinction, AI is not a language user because:

> Language [...] requires an intention to communicate.

Made clear by the example of ChatGPT being unable to _mean_ it when it says "I'm happy to see you".

Ending is stirring but not completely rigorous.

I like it best as meta-question of why do we create art why do we use language? There he puts the focus on intention.

That seems right to me but also limited, if we were looking for sincere intention in art, art would quickly get repetitive. We are looking for novelty too, or a response to what's came before that appears as novelty, or originality. Truthfulness is part of it, I wonder what the rest is?

]]></description>
            <link>https://garden.grantcuster.com/2024-09-01-11-06-33-Ted-Chiang-Why-AI-isnt-going-to-make-art</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://garden.grantcuster.com/2024-09-01-11-06-33-Ted-Chiang-Why-AI-isnt-going-to-make-art</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 11:06:33 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[2024-08-31-21-48-26]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Source, output, data. More wyswig work.

![](https://grant-uploader.s3.amazonaws.com/2024-08-31-21-48-13-2000.jpg)
]]></description>
            <link>https://garden.grantcuster.com/2024-08-31-21-48-26</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://garden.grantcuster.com/2024-08-31-21-48-26</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 21:48:26 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>