<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title><![CDATA[Grant's Garden]]></title>
        <description><![CDATA[Work and writing in progress]]></description>
        <link>https://garden.grantcuster.com</link>
        <image>
            <url>https://grant-uploader.s3.amazonaws.com/og-images/index.png</url>
            <title>Grant&apos;s Garden</title>
            <link>https://garden.grantcuster.com</link>
        </image>
        <generator>RSS for Node</generator>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 14:41:21 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://garden.grantcuster.com/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 14:41:21 GMT</pubDate>
        <managingEditor><![CDATA[Grant Custer]]></managingEditor>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[2024-09-15-10-37-37]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Organizing a new quotes repo: https://github.com/grantcuster/quotes

![pokemonsay hooked up to my quotes text file](https://grant-uploader.s3.amazonaws.com/2024-09-15-10-38-29-800.jpg)
]]></description>
            <link>https://garden.grantcuster.com/2024-09-15-10-37-37</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://garden.grantcuster.com/2024-09-15-10-37-37</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 14:37:37 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[2024-09-12-21-21-40]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[Inspired by dynamicland to try some real world manipulation linked to digital objects. I'd guessed coarse color matching would be enough here - it may not be.

![Red construction paper in real life moves sloth on computer](https://grant-uploader.s3.amazonaws.com/2024-09-12-21-22-59.gif)
]]></description>
            <link>https://garden.grantcuster.com/2024-09-12-21-21-40</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://garden.grantcuster.com/2024-09-12-21-21-40</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Sep 2024 01:21:40 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[2024-09-05-17-26-43-Wysywig-brainstorm]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[# Wysywig brainstorm

Demo that has some promise where all data is in the image file. Sources on the left, canvas layout on the top right. Data encoded as image pixels on the bottom right.

But I'm not excited to jump back into it lately so I need to figure something out.

I think it gets more interesting when I have the three ways of working with the images.

- The first way is like they're... images, the destination has them as movable, resizable boxes.
- The second way is like text. You have keybindings that print the image, and move you to the next square. One undecide piece here is are their text blocks? That complicates things, right? For their to be text blocks - maybe simplifies some things too, maybe they work kind of like they did in Sprout. Expanding out horizontally at first, to some max width then moving down. What is that data structure? Each char belongs to the text block... But that could also help explain why text gets laid out differently. It's not text that does, it's anything in this block. It's a layout in a block yea...
- The third way is paint, makes most sense with colors you could click and drag to print the same image... I guess like chars, a big part of the paint being useful is it should be able to break out of the box clumps - that's why you use it for something like annotation on top of other pieces. Maybe you group it together as you paint - i've done that before too.

But then it's more like a conventional image editor app. Maybe that's fine. I"ve tried to avoid layers before, hmmm...
]]></description>
            <link>https://garden.grantcuster.com/2024-09-05-17-26-43-Wysywig-brainstorm</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://garden.grantcuster.com/2024-09-05-17-26-43-Wysywig-brainstorm</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 21:26:43 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[2024-09-05-17-13-52-Hand-landmark-ideas]]></title>
            <description><![CDATA[# Hand landmark ideas

Brainstorming on the train. Laying out the pieces.

I can use mediapipe hand landmark. I know the positions of the fingers. I'll use pointer finger as cursor, if they have two hands up I can use both of them...

I can use pointer and thumb pincer as click. I can normalize distance based on lower knuckle thumb distance probably. Click and drag works with that motion too, although maybe it's a shame you can't just point and drag - maybe also some ability to toggle based on the other hand.

You could also try and distinguish point and drag from fist, so that raising one finger was the trigger - interesting you'd want to wait until it was fully raised though, probably need a little delay.

Idea to use your hand to 'freeze pixels' in a webcam just by dragging across an area... Question of when your fingers are 'live' and active.

Pixelate pixels by clicking, every click doubles the pixel area. That would actually work I think. I donder if I even grid it out in that case or just do it iteratively over the top... I think do it over the top but bigger pixels would overwrite smaller pixels. You'd want to set up pointerDown, pointerMove, pointerUp events, which would be fun in it's own right. And I guess you'd always track pointer as pointer... I think I'd need to chunk it up a bit though, because there's got to be some instability just sitting that there's not with a mouse or trackpad.

Maybe that's a good first demo. Pointerdown, pointermove, pointerup. What do you do when a hand goes offscreen? I think you keep it down if it's down huh? Till it comes back not down.

A bummer with webcam examples is I won't be able to write them on the train.
]]></description>
            <link>https://garden.grantcuster.com/2024-09-05-17-13-52-Hand-landmark-ideas</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://garden.grantcuster.com/2024-09-05-17-13-52-Hand-landmark-ideas</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 21:13:52 GMT</pubDate>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>